Guide to the Edward G. Levy Collection Relating to Temperance
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Edward G. Levy collection relating to temperance
1794-1970
1880-1970
GEN MSS 956
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.13
(4 boxes) + 2 art objects
Papers and other materials collected by Edward G. Levy, relating to temperance and prohibition, most 19th-early 20th centuries, most from the United States, with a small amount of material about temperance in Great Britain. Materials include documents and fragments, signed, by temperance advocates Marie Caroline Brehm, John B. Gough, Theobald Mathew, and John G. Woolley; a circular letter of the American Temperance Society, 1832; printed license and tax documents issued by the United States government, 1794-1929; clippings, including a scrapbook relating to the Woman's Christian Temperance Union in Connecticut, 1887-1888; postcards issued by the Association Against the Prohibition Amendment, undated; trade cards and other advertising materials of manufacturers of alcoholic beverages, circa 1865-1885 and undated; buttons, medals, and paper fans advertisting temperance organizations and beverage manufacturers, 1895-1930s and undated; and beverage bottles, bottle labels, and a brass whiskey tap, undated.
Levy, Edward G., 1898-1990
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edward G. Levy, 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 6 (glass beverage bottles): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Edward G. Levy (1898-1990)
Edward G. Levy received his LL.B from Boston University in 1921 and joined his brother's New Haven law practice. In 1939 he was sentenced to a year in jail for his participation in a kickback scheme led by the mayor of Waterbury. In later years he and his wife, Hortense R. Levy, collected autographs and dime novels and made substantial donations of these materials to several libraries. Edward G. Levy died in 1990.
Scope and Contents
Papers and other materials collected by Edward G. Levy, relating to temperance and prohibition, most nineteenth-early twentieth centuries, most from the United States, with a small amount of material about temperance in Great Britain. Materials include documents and fragments, signed, by temperance advocates Marie Caroline Brehm, John B. Gough, Theobald Mathew, and John G. Woolley; a circular letter of the American Temperance Society, 1832; printed license and tax documents issued by the United States government, 1794-1929; clippings, including a scrapbook relating to the Woman's Christian Temperance Union in Connecticut, 1887-1888; postcards issued by the Association Against the Prohibition Amendment, undated; trade cards and other advertising materials of manufacturers of alcoholic beverages, circa 1865-1885 and undated; buttons, medals, and paper fans advertisting temperance organizations and beverage manufacturers, 1895-1930s and undated; and beverage bottles, bottle labels, and a brass whiskey tap, undated.
Arrangement
Organized in to three series: I. Documents, 1794-1930s. II. Printed Material, 1850s-1970s. III. Objects, 1895-1930s.
Prohibition -- United States; Temperance -- Great Britain; Temperance -- Great Britain -- Societies, etc.; Temperance -- United States; Temperance -- United States -- Societies, etc.; Bottle labels (paper labels) -- United States -- 20th Century; Bottles -- United States -- 20th Century; Buttons (information artifacts) -- United States -- 20th Century; Fans (costume accessories) -- United States -- 20th Century; Matchbooks -- United States -- 20th Century; Medals -- United States -- 19th century; Plumbing fixtures -- United States -- 20th Century; Scrapbooks -- United States -- Connecticut -- 19th century; Trade cards (advertising) -- United States -- 19th century; Brehm, Marie Caroline, -1926; Demorest, William Jennings, 1822-1895; Gough, John B. (John Bartholomew), 1817-1886; Levy, Edward G., 1898-1990; Mathew, Theobald, 1790-1856; Nation, Carry Amelia, 1846-1911 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Woolley, John G. (John Granville), 1850-1922; American Temperance Society; Association Against the Prohibition Amendment; Woman's Christian Temperance Union
- Documents, 1794-1930s, undated; Series I; 0.34
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by name, followed by unsorted documents.
  - American Temperance Society. Circular letter, printed, 1832 November (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brehm, Marie Caroline. Note, autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gough, John B. (John Bartholomew). Notes, autograph manuscript, signed, and fragments, signed, 1878-1883, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gough, John B. (John Bartholomew). Address presented to Gough by Neath (Wales) temperance societies, manuscript and print, 1879 March 26 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 26)
  - Low, Nicholas. Receipt, manuscript in an unidentified hand, 1798 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mathew, Theobald. Autograph letter, signed, to "Mr. Watson", 1845 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Nation, Carry Amelia. Caricatures, in pencil, by an unidentified artist, undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 33)
  - United States government, 1794-1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes licenses and tax stamps for alcoholic beverages
  - United States government. Tax stamps for liquor, 1870s (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 27)
  - Woolley, John G. (John Granville). Note, autograph manuscript, signed, 1850 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Unsorted documents, 1795-1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Unsorted documents, 1849, circa 1930s (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 28)
- Printed Material, 1850s-1970s, undated; Series II; 0.56
  Arranged alphabetically by name, title, or type of material, followed by unsorted printed materials.
  - Association Against the Prohibition Amendment. 45 "Prohibition -Probes" postcards, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Bottle labels. 71 manufacturers' labels for wine, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bottle labels. 29 manufacturers' labels for beer, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bottle labels. 148 manufacturers' labels for liquor, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Clippings. Scrapbook, 1887-1888 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 29)
    Contains clippings about the Woman's Christian Temperance Union in Connecticut
  - Unsorted clippings, circa 1880-1970s; 2 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Unsorted clippings, 1855-1972 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 30)
  - Dime Novel Roundup. Volume 37, Numbers 11-12, 1968 November-December (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Contains articles by J. Edward Leithead about temperance stories
    With article by Leithead for Volume 37, Number 13, typescript and typescript carbon, signed
  - Matchbooks advertising alcoholic beverages, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Trade cards of manufacturers of alcoholic beverages, circa 1865-1885, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Unsorted printed material, circa 1900-1970s; 4 (Box 2, Folder 20-23)
  - Unsorted printed material, circa 1850s-1970s (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 31)
  - Unsorted printed material, undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 32)
- Objects, 1895-1930s, undated; Series III; 1.31
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material, followed by unsorted objects.
  - Buttons and medals, undated; 4 (Box 5 (Art), Folder 35-38)
    Issued by temperance organizations or manufacturers of alcoholic beverages
  - Paper fans, circa 1930s, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Issued by the Woman's Christian Temperance Union
  - Medal, awarded for the William Jennings Demorest prohibition prize, 1895 (Box 5 (Art), Folder 39)
  - Unidentified medals, undated (Box 5 (Art), Folder 40)
  - Brass whisky tap, undated; 1; (1 object) (Box 5 (Art), Folder 41)
    Accompanied by vendor receipt
  - Unsorted objects, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Unsorted objects, undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 34)
- Restricted Fragile Material, 0.67; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 6 (glass beverage bottles): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Glass beverage bottles, undated; (7 glass bottles) (Box 6 (Art), Folder 42)